Moving on to endocarditis,
this is inflammation of the endocardium,
particularly the endocardium that lines
the surface of cardiac valves.
Now recall that the heart basically contains three layers.
There's an endocardium, there's a myocardium,
and then there is a epicardium.
Remember that the endocardium lines
the inner surface of the heart.
It's basically a single layer of cells
sitting on top of a basement membrane.
They're basically endothelial cells.
And that this endocardium also lines
the surface of the cardiac valves as they project out.
And so in endocarditis, you're gonna get inflammation
predominantly on the surface of those cardiac valves.
Now this is usually due to bacterial infection,
not always, but usually.
The first high yield bug to be aware of is strep viridans.
This is the most common overall cause of endocarditis,
and it is a low virulence organism.
Now that's important because number one,
therefore, it can only infect previously damaged valves.
For example, if the valve is damaged
by chronic rheumatic heart disease
or mitral valve prolapse, then and only then
will this low virulence organism be able to infect it.
And number two, because it's low virulence,
it results in small vegetations
that will not destroy the valve.
And so that's particularly high yield,
but all of that's based on the low virulence of the organism.
In fact, the endocarditis caused by strep viridans
is also called subacute.
Now the pathogenesis is that because you've got
a previously damaged valve,
that damaged endocardial surface will expose subendothelial
collagen and tissue factor underneath it.
That then allows for the development of thrombotic
vegetations, and those vegetations, of course,
contain both platelets and fibrin.
Now these vegetations, they act as a trap for bacteria
whenever there's transient bacteria in the blood.
So for example, let's say that there's a dental procedure
and that forces bacteria into the blood.
Some of those bacteria can then be trapped
in these thrombotic vegetations on the heart valves,
which will then result in infectious endocarditis.
And that's one reason, for example,
the classic teaching was that prophylaxis with antibiotics,
for example, during the time of dental procedure,
could theoretically decrease the risk of endocarditis
in patients with damaged valves.
Staph aureus is the most common cause of endocarditis
in IV drug abusers.
It is a high virulence organism.
Therefore, it will infect normal valves,
and it will result in large vegetations
that destroy the valve.
Hence, it causes something called acute endocarditis.
Now important to know that the classic valve
that's going to be involved by Staph aureus
is the tricuspid.
Again, the idea is that the IV drug abuser
has contaminated skin and then shoots up
through the contaminated skin.
When they do so, the Staph aureus gets into the vein,
gets drained into the right heart eventually,
and then hits the tricuspid valve
and will damage the tricuspid valve.
Here's a picture of Staph aureus endocarditis.
You'll notice that these are very large vegetations
sitting on the cardiac valve,
and of course, this is also called acute endocarditis.
Staph epidermidis is important because it is the key bug
that causes endocarditis of prosthetic valves,
so that's the high yield there,
and Strep bulvis is important because it is the key bug
that causes endocarditis in patients
with underlying colorectal carcinoma.
Now, this is very high yield for board exam purposes,
even for clinics for that matter.
If you have a patient with endocarditis
who ends up having endocarditis due to Strep bulvis,
the next thing you need to do
is check for colorectal carcinoma,
and so that's a particularly important association
for board examinations.
Now, it's also possible to get endocarditis
with a group of organisms called the Haysack organisms.
This word basically represents the key organisms
that can cause this type of endocarditis.
They include Haemophilus, Actinobacillus,
Cardiobacterium, Iconella, and Kingella,
and the key thing about this endocarditis
is that it gives you endocarditis
with negative blood cultures,
and that's of course because these organisms
are particularly difficult to grow,
and so again, endocarditis with negative blood cultures.
Think about the Haysack organisms.
Clinically, irrespective of the cause of endocarditis,
patients generally have fever,
and they also have a murmur.
Now, the reason they have a murmur
is because they've got these vegetations
on the cardiac valves,
which is then going to disrupt flow across those valves.
In addition, they can get septic embolization
of the vegetations on the valve.
Now again, the idea is that if this is the valve
coming off the wall of the heart,
you've got these vegetations sitting on top of the valve,
and of course, the vegetations are going to be
flapping up and down with the valve,
and so these vegetations can be shot off into the circulation,
and when they're shot off into the circulation,
that would eventually result in septic emboli
of these tiny pieces of bacteria.
Complications of septic embolizations include
Janeway lesions,
and these are erythematous, non-tender lesions
on the palms and the soles,
and Osler nodes, which are painful lesions
on the fingers or toes,
and the way to remember this is,
ouch, ouch, Osler,
and so that's the one that's painful, if that helps you.
In addition, you can get splinter hemorrhages in the nail bed,
and that again would be due to septic embolization,
and so these are some of the key findings
that arise with septic embolization.
Now finally, the patients can also have
anemia of chronic disease.
Of course, they've got chronic inflammation
because they've got this infectious endocarditis,
which can then lead to anemia of chronic disease.
Now the laboratory findings are that the patient
will generally have a positive blood culture.
There will be the findings of anemia of chronic disease,
and just recall that if they have anemia of chronic disease,
that's going to be generally a microcytic anemia,
and so the hemoglobin would be low because there's anemia.
The MCV would be low because it's usually microcytic.
Of course, in this particular case,
you've got acute phase reactants being released by the liver.
One particular acute phase reactants would be hepcidin.
Remember, hepcidin is high yield.
It traps iron in the storage sites,
and so when iron is trapped in the storage sites,
the ferritin will be high.
Because the ferritin is high, the TiVC will be low,
and in addition, because there's no access to iron
from the storage sites,
the bone marrow will begin to take iron from the blood,
and so the serum iron will decrease,
and the percent saturation will decrease.
Now in addition, transesophageal echo can be used
for detecting lesions on the valves,
and this is a very good way to be able to look for those
vegetations on the valve that are so characteristic
of endocarditis.
Another type of endocarditis is called
non-bacterial thrombotic endocarditis.
The name tells you a lot, it's not due to bacteria.
Instead, you get thrombotic vegetations
on the cardiac valves.
These are sterile vegetations.
They generally are associated with a hypercoagulable state
or an underlying adenocarcinoma in the patient.
These vegetations usually arise on the mitral valve,
along the lines of closure,
and they'll result in regurgitation.
Liebman-Sachs endocarditis is particularly high yield.
We've discussed it previously.
This is where you get sterile vegetations
in association with lupus.
Now the most important thing here is that
if you've got this valve,
you get vegetations on both sides of the cardiac valve.
And when you get vegetations on both sides,
that's highly characteristic of Liebman-Sachs endocarditis.
Again, it usually involves the mitral valve,
and it's gonna result in mitral valve regurgitation.
And that completes our section on endocarditis.